Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

■ pedro.harunari@uni.lu | # November 15th, 1995 | ↑ pedroharunari.github.io/website/

Personal Profile

Currently, I hold a postdoctoral researcher position at the University of Luxembourg, working under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where I engaged in extensive research and teaching activities. As an active researcher in statistical physics, my focus is on understanding and taming fluctuations of systems outside thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. I am particularly interested in extending the description of stochastic thermodynamics in the presence of hidden degrees of freedom by pinpointing the relevant quantities, deriving practical expressions for real-world challenges, and connecting to the study of phase transitions, biophysics, chemical reaction networks, complex systems, and more.

Education

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Postdoctoral researcher

Dec 2022 - Current

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Doctorate in Physics Mar 2018 - Nov 2022

- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Carlos E. Fiore
- Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- · Approved with the highest grades in every course
- · Teaching assistant experience during three semesters, both in graduate and undergraduate levels

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

2022

2020

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- One semester as teaching assistant
- · Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

List of Publications

8 articles published in internationally renowned journals and one preprint.

From Google Scholar: 124 citations, h-index 7.

PE Harunari, A Garilli, and M Polettini, "The beat of a current"
 Physical Review E 107 (4), L042105
 PE Harunari, A Dutta, M Polettini, and E Roldán, "What to learn from a few visible transitions' statistics?"

Physical Review X **12**, 041026

IN Mamede, PE Harunari, BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from

interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings"

Physical Review E **105** (2), 024106

CE Fiore, PE Harunari, CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions"

Physical Review E **104** (6), 064123

PE Harunari, S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, "Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric interaction times"

Physical Review Research **3** (2), 023194

PE Harunari, CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, "Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump"

Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical **53** (37), 374001

CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing

• nonequilibrium phase transitions"

June 13, 2023

Physical Review E 100 (1), 012104 2019

JM Encinas, PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase

transitions in the inertial majority vote model"

Scientific reports 8 (1), 1-9 2018

PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority

vote model"

Physical Review E 96 (4), 042305 2017

Work Experience

(Post)Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer

Dec 2022

- · Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg
- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

May 2022 - Jun 2022

Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Visiting researcher

Apr 2021 - Feb 2022 • Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.

· Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

University of Aalto Helsinki, Finland

Visiting researcher Dec 2021 - Jan 2022

· Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

Statistical Physics seminar series

online

Organizer

· 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across

Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Teaching assistant 2018 - 2020

- Thermodynamics (2020);
- Statistical Mechanics (2018 and 2019);
- · Graduate level Statistical Mechanics (2018).

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Undergraduate researcher

2015 - 2017

- · Research training program.
- Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

Skills

Programming Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, ETEX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

JUNE 13, 2023

Prizes and Grants

2022 Best Ph.D. thesis prize , Institute of Physics - University of São Paulo	
2022 Honorable mention for distinguished publication , Institute of Physics - University of São	Paulo
2021 Intership grant , grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE - FAPESP)	
2018 Ph.D. fellowship , FAPESP 4 years grant for the Doctorate without Masters degree program	
2017 Undergrad research fellowship , FAPESP grant for the Undergraduate research program 2016 Undergrad research fellowship , CNPg grant for the Undergraduate research program	
2016 Undergrad research fellowship , CNPq grant for the Undergraduate research program	
Events attended	
XXVII Sitges Conference on Statistical Mechanics	Sitges, Spain
Universitat de Barcelona	2023
• <u>Talk</u> : "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"	
Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST IV	online
The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) • Talk: "Fluctuation relation at the beat of a current"	2023
Physics of Life: Students and Postdocs Edition	New York, United States of America
The Center for the Physics of Biological Function, CUNY/Princeton	2023
• <u>Talk</u> : "Thermodynamics through the lens of transitions"	
Fluctuations and First Passage Problems	Stockholm, Sweden
NORDITA	2023
• <u>Talk</u> : "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"	
Journées de Physique Statistique, 42nd edition	Paris, France
École Normale Supérieure de Paris • Talk: "Transition-based coarse-graining"	2023
The 47th Conference of the Middle European Cooperation in Statistical Physics	Erice, Italy
MECO 47	2022
Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	
Autumn meeting	São Paulo, Brazil
Brazilian Physical Society	2022
• Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	
National Statistical Physics Meeting	online
Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ)	2021
<u>Talk</u> : "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	
Statistical Physics of Complex Systems	Trieste, Italy
The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)	2021
Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions"	
Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII	online
International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS)	2021
Autumn meeting	online
Brazilian Physical Society Talk: "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions"	2021
Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST II	online
Santa Fe Institute	2021
APS March Meeting	online
American Physical Society	2021
• <u>Talk</u> : "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations"	
Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems	online
Donostia International Physics Center	2020
Statistical Physics Seminar Series	online
University of São Paulo	2020
<u>Talk</u> : "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR"	

JUNE 13, 2023

Autumn meeting online

Brazilian Physical SocietyTalk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties"

Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists

Bad Honnef, Germany

Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation

2020

• Poster: "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pump and its exact solution"

"Coloquinho" São Paulo, Brazil

series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students

2019

• Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects"

Physics Giants: Einstein Week

São Paulo, Brazil

series of talks organized by USP students

2010

• Invited talk: "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics"

Languages_

English Full professional proficiency

Portuguese Native proficiency

Spanish Llimited working proficiency

Peer-review contributions

(3) Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, (1) Journal of Physics Communications

JUNE 13, 2023